A Guide to the Ellett Family Papers 1865-1961
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ellett Family Papers 1865-1961
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms88-047
0.2 cu. ft., 1 box, 26 folders, 1 ledger
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from Katherine Hoge on September 5, 1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
Robert Thaddeus Ellett served as an assistant surgeon in the Confederate States Army from 1863-65, at which time he was assigned to a hospital in Montgomery White Sulphur Springs, VA. Prior to his appointment as assistant surgeon, Ellett served as Captain of the Pamunkey Artillery, Virginia Heavy Artillery, Confederate States Army from May, 1861 until his resignation on September 3, 1862. Two months after the Civil War, Ellett was pardoned at Charleston, West Virginia on June 14, 1865 as a Surgeon, Provisional Army of the Confederate States.
Scope and Content
The Ellett family papers consist of 35 correspondence letters written by Dr. Robert Thaddeus Ellett (1826-1904) who served as assistant surgeon in White Sulphur Springs, Virginia, for the Confederate States during the Civil War. His letters are written to Sue French of Pearisburg, who would later become Ellett's wife.
The Ellett collection also includes one ledger of Ellett's medical accounts, categorized by patient. Other items include biographical and family history information, photos, clippings, a 1961 dedication to Col. W. H. French marker program, DAR applications, and "The Family Album," an eleven page typescript.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Ellett Family Papers 1865-1961
  - Letters from Robert Thaddeus Ellett to Sue French 1865-67
    - May 22, 1865 (Box-folder 1-1)
    - February 5, 1866 (Box-folder 1-2)
    - May 25, 1866 (Box-folder 1-3)
    - October 17, 1866 (Box-folder 1-4)
    - November 26, 1866 (Box-folder 1-5)
    - November 30, 1866 (Box-folder 1-6)
    - December 14, 1866 (Box-folder 1-7)
    - December 21, 1866 (Box-folder 1-8)
    - January 6, 1867 (Box-folder 1-9)
    - January 14, 1867 (Box-folder 1-10)
    - January 18, 1867 (Box-folder 1-11)
    - January 21, 1867 (Box-folder 1-12)
    - January 27, 1867 (Box-folder 1-13)
    - February 14, 1867 (Box-folder 1-14)
    - February 22, 1867 (Box-folder 1-15)
    - March 4, 1867 (Box-folder 1-16)
    - March 22, 1867 (Box-folder 1-17)
    - April 19, 1867 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Letters written to Sue French 1867-92, n.d. (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Letters written to Dr. Robert T. Ellett, includes copy of deed and contract (2) 1875-1900, n.d. (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Genealogical information on the Ellett and French families (letters, death dates, compiled information) 1905-49, n.d. (Box-folder 1-21)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution membership applications (2) 1911 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Description of "The Southern Cross of Honor" 1918 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Miscellaneous 1949-61, n.d. (Box-folder 1-24)
    Includes photographs and a program taken from the dedication of Colonel William Henderson French marker, a newspaper article describing the death of George Washington, and a copy of the pardon of James H. Hoge, issued by President Andrew Johnson.
  - "The Family Album," an eleven page typescript, first person narrative (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Extracts from "A History of the Middle New River Settlements," by David E. Johnston n.d. (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Medical Fee Book of Robert T. Ellett 1867-1872